מזל טוב. Mazel Tov. We start a new מסכת, Masechet, מסכת גיטין.
Masechet Gittin. And I want to take a few minutes in the
beginning, by the way it’s a very short דף, Daf, if you
take a quick look you will see how few lines of גמרא
Gemara there are on this דף. Daf. So I want to take
a few, we’ll have a few a little extra time, I want
to take a few minutes to introduce the מסכת Masechet and the
topic. As far as the מסכת Masechet is concerned, it is like
a classic מסכת Masechet in the גמרא, Gemara, not one of those
funky things we did before with a funny language or not real
רש"י, Rashi, etc. It is a classic one because anything in נשים,
Nashim, נזיקין, Nezikin, pretty much anything is very classic.
You have the whole wealth of the ראשונים Rishonim on it. You
have
and it's one that's learned like I'm going to say classic too
many times in ישיבות Yeshivot on a very regular basis, a staple
of the ישיבה Yeshiva education. Now, not because obviously it's very הלכה
למעשה Halacha l'maaseh about the giving of a גט Get and so
on, but also as I'll talk about in a minute, it's very
packed with a lot of like deep conceptual issues and relevant ש"ס
Shas issues about שליחות Shlichus and שטרות Shtarot and ownership and conditions
on transactions. So it's got a lot of these deep ש"ס Shas
concepts. It's very conceptual, a lot of themes that continue and continue
to get referred back to and so on. So it's a very,
very rich מסכת. Masechet. If you want
now in terms of its organization, let me also say one thing,
well about before I get to the organization, which is one of
the I think almost sad things in the from the contemporary context
of learning מסכת גיטין Masechet Gittin is that, you know, you read
through the whole מסכת Masechet and the גמרא Gemara like any גמרא,
Gemara, like when it’s talking about ייבום Yibbum or whatever, the focus
is on the process, right? How do you write a גט Get
and how do you deliver a גט Get and all the whole
things, all the technical details or conceptual issues, etc. That's all about
the process, okay? But every page you're reading, it's like uncomplicated, not
that the הלכה Halacha is uncomplicated, but the social reality is uncomplicated
that of course a guy is giving a גט Get to his
wife, right? And it's just interesting in analyzing like what are the
nature of the process. So it's almost there's something about it that’s,
you know, the taken for granted nature of the fact that a
גט Get is a natural thing that would happen and so on
and we just have to work through the specifics and certainly knowing
how complicated almost every single divorce is nowadays because of the imbalance
of power. Now part of this was true because if you didn't
have a secular system, it's not just that they had a בית
דין Beis Din that could use its muscle. Sure that's true too
and you had a more tighter Jewish community and the בית דין
Beis Din had authority and they could use its muscle and they
were motivated to use its muscle, which is not the case sadly
a large part of the time in Israel and so on. That
was an understatement. Anyway, but besides that it's not just the issue
of muscle, it's that if you don't have a secular system
and society doesn't tolerate, you know, the guy let's say not, you
know, leaving his wife and shacking up with another woman and so
on, so if you wanted to end the marriage, this was the
only way you could end the marriage. So of course just like
now, if you want to get a divorce you have to get
a secular divorce. There's no עגונה, Aguna, you know, in the I
mean it is true sometimes like one of the spouses will refuse
to sign the divorce papers for one reason or another. You know
what I'm talking about in the secular system. But the point is
that so there was this there is that thing that there is
a little bit it's like it's just interesting that feeling we're going
to go through it and the giving of a גט Get will
be a natural taken for granted reality and the focus is going
to be on the Halachic aspects of it. Yes.
In much of Western European and American society divorce was basically not
possible
until the 20th century.
How did they legalize divorce in my lifetime?
There you go, having a lot to do with the Christian background.
Yeah. Okay. So in terms of the structure, let's say a word
about the structure. Okay? The first again like some מסכתות, Masechtot, it
does not begin with the basic issues, right? Let's talk about how
do you write a גט, Get, how do you give a גט.
Get. It sort of starts with a more interesting side point. Okay?
That's the way some מסכתות Masechtot begin. And it talks about המביא
גט ממדינת הים. Hameivi Get MiMedinat Hayam. Somebody is a שליח, Shliach,
an agent is delivering a גט Get from overseas and it talks
about what that agent has to testify to. Okay? And if you
take a look, I just want us to flip through the פרקים,
Perakim, the next פרק Perek continues I mean there's some interesting digressions
in the first one, but the next פרק Perek is also called
המביא גט. Hameivi Get. Okay? So it actually also continues with this
idea of delivering a גט Get and bringing a גט Get from
far away. But in the middle of the second פרק Perek you
start getting to some of the specifics about how a גט Get
is written. Okay? So you have הכל כותבין, Hakol Kotvin, you can
write with all types of inks. What happens if it's written in
the day and signed at night? What type of קלף Klaf do
you write on? You know, אין כותבין במחובר לקרקע. Ein Kotvin Bimchubar
Lakarka. So the middle of the second פרק Perek you start getting
to the specifics about how the גט Get is actually written. The
fact that it has to be done לשמה, Lishma, with the intent
of the woman in the with the woman in mind, etc. Okay,
and then you get into the third פרק, perek, continuing with some
of the, you know, the specifics of the writing and the given,
giving of the גט. get. Oh so I mention לשמה, lishma, if
the גט get is being delivered, can you assume that the guy
is still alive while it's being delivered? Okay, what, you know, interesting
types of questions of that nature. That gets into a digression of
can we go ahead and in general, if a שליח shaliach is
going to do something, can he assume the guy who sent him
is still alive? What assumptions can you make when you're not seeing
the person? Okay, the fourth פרק perek talks about if somebody sends
a שליח shaliach to deliver his גט get to his wife, it's
called השולח, ha-sholeach, and then he runs up and he cancels the
messenger's agency not in the messenger's presence. Okay, and then the messenger's
going to deliver the גט get to the wife and the wife
will think she's divorced, she'll marry, the kids will be ממזרים, mamzerim,
and none of this will have been true. So the rabbis instituted
something to prevent it, and then here we get to a little
type of rabbinic social activism, otherwise known as תיקון העולם. tikkun haolam.
Because of תיקון העולם, tikkun haolam, it says in the משנה, mishna,
that's where it comes from. Okay, the rabbis instituted certain laws and
sometimes
even sort of somehow manipulating certain דאורייתות d'oraissas in order to, for
the betterment of society. And then we get into a whole two
פרקים, prakim, the fourth and fifth פרק, perek, which is things that
the rabbis did מפני תיקון העולם. mipnei tikkun haolam. And we range
from נשים nashim to נזיקין nezikin to like all different types of
areas, well נשים nashim and נזיקין nezikin are the most interpersonal anyway,
and things related to תיקון עולם. tikkun olam. So that's like a
fun little middle section. Okay, and it's a lot. And then the
sixth פרק perek gets back to, you know, giving the גט, get,
and on and on till the end. And then one of the
other interesting things, I won't go through the whole specifics, but one
of the interesting things that comes up also is somebody who gives
a גט get on condition. Okay, and again in the משניות mishnayos
when you read it it's just like okay on the condition you
do this, that, whatever, like a trivial type of a thing. And
the focus there isn't about extortion and blackmail, it's just about how
do you stipulate a condition, you know, and what makes something a
legitimate תנאי tnai in the, like in a contract. And then towards
the end we get to actual the delivery of the גט, get,
what it means for a woman to receive it. And then at
the very, very end of the מסכתא, masechta, we finally get to
what is considered to be the proper conditions for which a man
should divorce his wife, like the last משנה. mishna. So anyway, but
as you can tell a very rich and diverse מסכתא. masechta. What
I also want to say, and then we will get actually to
beginning reading this, but I just cannot resist saying and this shows
you about, you know, about, like how רמב"ם, Rambam, you know, his
sort of systematic approach to things,
brilliance, the way he begins his הלכות גירושין. Hilchos Gerushin. I would
recommend that people read his פרק א perek aleph of הלכות גירושין
Hilchos Gerushin because what he does is he starts us off by
saying there're ten conditions דאורייתא d'oraisa to make a גט get a
כשר kosher גט. get. And he lists them, I'll tell you what
they are in a minute. And then he says and here's the
פסוק pasuk it's based on. And it's all based on one פסוק
pasuk in the תורה. Torah. Right? What's the פסוק? pasuk? כי יקח
איש אשה ki yikach ish isha whatever ומצא בה ערות דבר u’matza
ba ervat davar
no no what is it? והיה אם לא תמצא חן בעיניו. ve-haya
im lo timtza chen be’einav.
Yeah, what's the פסוק, pasuk, what's before וכתב לה ספר כריתות? ve-kasav
la sefer kerisus? Anyway לא מצא חן בעיניו lo matza chen be’einav
is that it?
I think so. לא מצא חן בעיניו כי מצא בה ערות דבר.
lo matza chen be’einav ki matza ba ervat davar. Okay. כי מצא
בה ערות דבר. ki matza ba ervat davar. So that's the background
to condition which has to do with what is the, what are
the conditions under which, oops, under which we think a person, a
man, excuse me, should be writing a גט, get, should be divorcing
his wife. And anyway here's the big פסוק. pasuk. וכתב לה ספר
כריתות
ונתן בידה
ושלחה מביתו.
ve-kasav la sefer kerisus ve-nasan
beyada ve-shilcha
mibeiso. Okay. That's the key. So these one, two, three, four, five,
six, seven, eight words is the entire all of the דאורייתא d'oraisa
laws of גיטין Gittin basically hinge on these eight words. And the
רמב"ם Rambam more than one law per word. And here's and basically
here's what the רמב"ם Rambam says. Okay, I'll just read you the
רמב"ם. Rambam. He says, okay, here are the ten conditions. He says
וכתב לה ספר כריתות ושלחה מביתו ve-kasav la sefer kerisus ve-shilcha mibeiso
אם לא תמצא חן בעיניו, im lo timtza chen be’einav, מלמד שאינו
מגרש אלא ברצונו. melamed she-eino megaresh ela birtzono. And with אם לא
תמצא חן בעיניו im lo timtza chen be’einav anyway לא מצא חן
בעיניו lo matza chen be’einav
anyway
this has to be מרצונו. mirtzono. He has to do it willingly.
Now in general all transactions have to be with your דעת daas
and intent so we can talk about what makes the willingly more
specific to גיטין. Gittin. אינו מגרש eino megaresh fine.
But the woman, אבל האשה מתגרשת ברצונה ושלא ברצונה. aval ha-isha mitgereshet
birtzonah veshe-lo birtzonah. The woman is divorced even against her will. וכתב,
ve-kasav, אינה מתגרשת אלא בכתב. eina mitgereshet ela bichtav. Okay,
this is condition number one. Two, it has to be a writ,
that's pretty obvious. Actually פשטא דפסוקים. p'shata de-pasukim. Okay.
לה
לשמה. lah lishmah. It has to be written with her specifically in
mind. It cannot be written and just you have a generic גט
get or you weren't thinking of the particular woman, etc. Okay. ספר
כריתות, sefer kritut, דבר הכורת בינו ובינה, davar ha-koret beino u-veinah, שלא
ישאר עליו רשות. she-lo yisha'er alav rashut.
So basically he says, you're divorced from me but there's some, not
a condition to make it take effect but an ongoing way in
which she's not fully divorced. You're divorced from me but every single
week you have to do X, right? Or you're, you know, there's
something that is not fully severing
about the act, that he makes some, he holds back something and
makes some ongoing stipulation that she's not fully severing. Okay, it has
to be דבר הכורת, davar ha-koret, and we'll see what that means,
fully severing.
Okay. How are we going to get six more conditions out of
those words? Let's take a look. Okay. ונתן בידה, ve-natan be-yadah, אלא
שניתן גט לידה. ela she-nitan get le-yadah.
So obviously it has to reach her, okay, or her messenger, or
go into her property.
Okay, that's obvious. ושלחה. ve-shillachah.
He has to be, he is sending her away. He has to
say, I am divorcing you, not you are, and you know, not
it can be like I am, you, you know, as the רמב"ם
Rambam says, הרי את משולחת, harei at meshulachat, הרי את מגורשת, harei
at megureshet,
that works. Okay, but he cannot say שישלח עצמו ממנה, she-yishlach atzmo
mimennah,
I am leaving you. You are divorced from me, I'm not leaving
you, okay? So he has to, she is divorced, the language of
the גט, get, from him, sending her, like she is the one
being sent away. That's the language of the גט, get, the text
of the
גט. get. פרשה? parsha? Right, right. Well, it's also the reality of
a patriarchal society. Okay, right. Okay,
or
what and it also that, right, and it's also, right, and it's
also refers to the separation, it can't just say, you are now
a free woman. Okay, it has to specifically refer to the act
of you are being divorced from me, you are being sent away
from me.
Okay, now, we're not done yet.
Okay. וכתב ונתן. ve-katav ve-natan. Okay, so this is a trickier one,
because here we only have how many? Six. Okay, so the combination
of וכתב
ונתן ve-katav ve-natan tell
us there cannot be anything separating, nothing between writing and giving. Now
we don't mean there can't be any time, obviously there can be
a lot of time, but what we mean is, for example, you
can't write on מחובר. mechubar. That's one classic example, not on מחובר.
mechubar. You can't write on a tree that then the only way
it is possible to give it would be you'd have to cut
down the tree. Okay. So you cannot, you can have time, you
can do a million things between the writing and the giving, but
you can't be in a situation where it's necessary to do something
between the writing and the giving. Okay, so that's that, that's a
smaller point.
Or even in the condition because you can do a תנאי. t'nai.
What? I can do a תנאי. t'nai.
You can do a תנאי, t'nai, but that's not, yeah, that's true,
but it's not somehow necessary. No, but it's not the giving, that's
the taking the effect, the חלות chalot of it, not the act
of giving it. This is the physical, right, the writing of the
horn of an animal, fine. We'll talk about that.
Okay, now, ספר כריתות ונתן
בידה.
sefer kritut ve-natan
be-yadah. This, oh, I
see I need another color to show, well to show that when
we're doing the combination of words.
Anyway, so this combination, okay, ספר כריתות ונתן בידה, sefer kritut ve-natan
be-yadah, is it
has to be given as a גט. get. It can't be like,
you know, when they give
those, what do you call it, subpoenas, okay, and they trick the
guy into accepting it because it's like, you know, so you know,
you know, they do that on like movies or whatever. You gotta
serve a subpoena and like you say, here, hold on to this
document, you're now served. Okay, so here it has to be explicitly
given as a גט. get. It can't, man can't say to his
wife, here, take this letter, you know, here, could you hold on
to this piece of paper for me? You're now divorced. You can't
say that, it has to be given as a גט. get. Okay,
that's eight. And let's just do nine and ten.
What? דיינו? dayenu?
Oh, it has to be in front of עדים, edim, that's the
one thing not in this פסוק. pasuk. עדים edim is based on
the basic idea of על פי שנים עדים יקום דבר. al pi
shenayim edim yakum davar. So that's
the one thing not based on this פסוק. pasuk.
It has to be given in front of עדים. edim.
It has to be given in front of עדים edim or עדים
edim have to sign it. That's a debate in the גמרא, Gemara,
whether it's about being given in front of עדים edim or עדים
edim have to sign it. Not written though, you could have said
not written in front of עדים, edim, not written in front of
עדים. edim. And the tenth one is, is that
the
husband...
Okay, or
a giving and taking it?
Yeah I don't know as opposed let's say to the court delivering
the גט. get. Okay, so those are the ten requirements דאורייתא d'Oraita
requirements or דרבנן, d'Rabbanan, all learned out from like eight these eight
words and this other פסוק pasuk about עדים. edim.
You said they're all דאורייתא d'Oraita even when she writes the גט?
get? No, I'm sorry if I said that I did not mean
that.
No you didn't, I just okay, how
did the עדים edim fit we'll see that, we'll see the whole
עדים edim thing, that's a separate conversation. Are these all דאורייתא d'Oraita
or דאורייתא. d'Oraita. Okay, so the רמב"ם's Rambam brilliant way of giving
you an overview of the מסכת Masechet and linking it to these
eight words in the פסוק. pasuk. We're not going to get to
the דאורייתאs d'Oraita for a few weeks, okay? But I wanted since
it is a very short דף, daf, I wanted to start with
an appreciation
of what constitutes a גט get from the תורה's Torah perspective.
Kind of like the same thing with מזוזה, Mezuzah, ten conditions.
Yeah, but here that he quotes a פסוק pasuk and shows you
each piece of the פסוק, pasuk, it's very yeah, it's very right,
it's great. Okay, so now let's take a look with all that
said as an introduction to the מסכת Masechet and to the topic
of גיטין, Gittin, let's open to the first דף. daf. All right.
המביא גט ממדינת הים. Hamavi get mimedinat hayam.
Somebody brings a גט get from overseas. תוספות Tosafot points out that
רש"י Rashi says כל חוץ לארץ קרי ליה מדינת הים, kol chutz
la'aretz karei lei medinat hayam, it means anywhere outside of ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, but תוספות Tosafot says I think more correctly that אף
על גב ד af al gav d' first of all it says
מדינת הים, medinat hayam, תוספות Tosafot says הא דלא נקט המביא גט
מחוץ לארץ, hadei lo nakat hamavi get michutz la'aretz, second תוספות. Tosafot.
המביא גט בספינה כבי מחוץ לארץ, Hamavi get besfinah kivei michutz la'aretz,
משום דבחוץ לארץ הוי משמע כל חוץ לארץ, mishum d'bechutz la'aretz havei
mashma kol chutz la'aretz,
etc. But מדינת הים medinat hayam suggests more far away, a distant
place, it's more distant from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, and we'll talk
about that in a bit. So somebody brings a גט get from
from overseas to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, צריך שיאמר בפני נכתב ובפני
נחתם. tzarich sheyomar befanai nechtav uvfanai nechtam. When he delivers the גט,
get, this is a messenger, he has to say and he's going
to give it to the woman, he has to make a declaration
in front of a בית דין Beis Din presumably or somebody at
least witnesses, this was written and sealed in my pre and signed
in my presence. Now we're going to see in the גמרא Gemara
why does he have to say that? I mean that's the most
obvious question. What are we concerned about? And the גמרא's Gemara going
to have two opinions, one based on the fact that he says
it was written in my presence and the other back to the
fact that it was signed in my presence. The most obvious one
is why do you think it's important that a person delivering a
גט get has to testify that it was signed in his presence?
So that we know that these are real עדים edim and that
it's of effect.
How do you know that the husband did this altogether? Somebody who
wants to marry the woman is forging this whole thing or somebody
who wants to cause the woman צרות tzarot or whatever. The husband
is not standing in front of us, right? We have no idea
like he doesn't have to bring an affidavit that the husband made
him a שליח, shaliach, like we have no idea who this guy
is. A guy shows up on a doorstep with a גט. get.
So he has to testify to the fact that it was properly
signed by the husband and he is a witness of the husband,
even then he could be lying but that's what he has to
testify to. Okay, the written part we'll see in the גמרא Gemara
is a way of saying it was the writing of the גט
get was done correctly. Okay, so that meaning if it was written
לשמן lishman because these requirements were satisfied. The writing of the גט
get so he is bringing a גט, get, we don't know who
he is, we don't know who sent him, we don't know what
this piece of paper is in front of us, how it was
written, right? So he is testifying to the legitimacy of what he
is presenting. It was written and signed in front of me.
Now would this be the
same thing if it was חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz חוץ לארץ? chutz
la'aretz? We will talk about that. רבן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Gamliel omer,
now רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says אף המביא מרקם ומהגר. af hamavi
mirekem umehager.
Even if you don't bring from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, even from
מדינת הים, medinat hayam, even if you bring from רקם Rekem and
הגר. Hager. Now where's רקם Rekem and הגר? Hager? Big תוספות Tosafot
tries to figure out where it is. Seems like there were תוספות
Tosafot says there are two רקם Rekem and הגרs, Hager sometimes that
sounds like a cheap answer, but if you actually speak to archaeologists
there sometimes are a lot of places in that region with the
same name place. Okay, anyway clearly this seems to be some place
that is very close to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, תוספות Tosafot thinks
that maybe it's in the land of פלשתים, Plishtim, which would actually
suggest that it's in what, like the Gaza Strip, although I don't
think so because that would not be considered outside close and outside,
that would be considered in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Anyway, but תוספות
Tosafot thinks that these are places that clearly are very close to
the border of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So he is saying even
somebody who brings רש"י Rashi associates it with the biblical קדש Kadesh
and ברד, Bared, which is where הגר Hagar runs when she is
driven out by שרה. Sarah. So it seems like it is close
to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Even somebody who brings from there has
to say it. Okay and we'll see in the גמרא Gemara how
close it is and what the implications of that are. רבי אליעזר
אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, אפילו מכפר לודיים ללוד. afilu mikfar Ludim le-Lud.
Even if somebody brings from the village of לודיים Ludim to לוד.
Lud. Now there's two questions here, which is number one is, well
I don't understand, what's חוץ לארץ? chutz la'aretz? I mean לוד Lud
is like not at a border of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Did
they actually think that that was on the border that they had
a narrower a much narrower strip at that northern part than we
normally imagine? That's like not at all clear why he's saying that.
Also תוספות Tosafot wants to know Why he says לוד, Lud, why
didn't he say אפילו מכפר לודים? afilu mikfar ludim? Right? You're saying
where you bring it from. Who cares where you're delivering it to?
You're bringing it from a city.
The point is right well okay the point is though the first
point is like even if you bring from places what these תנאים
Tanaim are saying is even if you bring from places near Israel
you still have to say it doesn't have to be far away.
מדינת הים Medinat Hayam suggests far away they're saying even if it's
near. So why does it say from כפר לודים Kfar Ludim to
לוד? Lud? So one answer תוספות Tosafot says is pretty much what
what Michael said which is you would have assumed that even if
for some reason כפר לודים Kfar Ludim is over the border which
is a strange idea that it's just over the border from לוד
Lud anyway you would have assumed that since it's conceptually like the
you know the suburbs of לוד Lud you wouldn't treat it as
a separate place and it wouldn't matter if technically it's over the
border. The other point תוספות Tosafot makes out is that רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer himself was from לוד Lud so he was giving this
as an example. Okay but anyway what these תנאים Tanaim are clearly
saying and the גמרא Gemara is going to analyze it more specifically
is even if you bring from places they don't have to be
way far מדינת הים Medinat Hayam even if you bring places right
near the border okay and just over the line and maybe even
if it's just even just a suburb
you would still have to say when you bring from outside of
Israel.
Now וחכמים אומרים Vechachamim Omrim and the sages say אינו צריך לומר
בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם eino tzarich lomar bifanay nechtav uvifanay nechtam אלא
המביא ממדינת הים. ela hameivi mimedinat hayam. No only if it's really
from
overseas. והמוליך Vehamolich or there's something to add okay now the question
is where do where do the חכמים Chachamim end and where do
we resume the תנא קמא? Tanna Kamma? Okay they could you could
say only really overseas period. No it's got to be real overseas
end of story and then we're back to the סתם Stam voice
of the משנה Mishnah or they could be saying only really overseas
plus if you go in the reverse direction as well. If you
bring it from Israel to you know to מדינת הים. Medinat Hayam.
More logically right you would put the period after אלא המביא ממדינת
הים ela hameivi mimedinat hayam period. Cause the first set of debate
is does it have to be you know really distant or even
just over the border? Okay now we go back to the anonymous
voice of the משנה Mishnah okay והמוליך vehamolich
so if you bring it from מדינת הים Medinat Hayam or if
you're מוליך molich you bring it from Israel to מדינת הים Medinat
Hayam you don't you know okay so והמביא ממדינה למדינה במדינת הים
vehameivi mimedina limedina bimedinat hayam or let's say it's not about bringing
about bringing it from Israel to overseas or vice versa but from
one country to another country outside of Israel okay in all of
those conditions you would have to do it. Okay so then you
wonder why mention Israel cause then the basic point is one country
to another country. So the גמרא Gemara is going to imagine two
countries within Israel let's say יהודה Yehuda and גליל Galil I mean
what is considered a country a מדינה medina right wasn't necessarily a
nation-state exactly. So anyway so that for example so from יהודה Yehuda
to גליל Galil in Israel you wouldn't have to seems to be
the point but okay
not necessarily two cities in מדינה. medina.
Right maybe from one city to another within one מדינה medina you
might not have to okay. But anyway the משנה Mishnah is saying
you bring it from חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to מדינת הים Medinat Hayam or one מדינה
medina to another מדינה medina in מדינת הים Medinat Hayam one minute
צריך לומר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. tzarich lomar bifanay nechtav uvifanay nechtam.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer אפילו מהגמוניא
להגמוניא. afilu mehegmonia lehegmonia.
Now this is getting to Michael's question הגמוניא hegmonia sounds like the
word hegemony הגמוניא hegmonia hegemony right. It's a Greek word yes which
is a Greek word which means like whatever like rulership or something
and he basically means the way this sounds like the way the
גמרא Gemara explains it is even if in one city you have
like you have like East and West Berlin okay and one city
you have two different rulers over different parts of the city you
know even there you would have good example right even there you
would have to go ahead and bring so certainly from one city
to another city in the same מדינה medina okay. But even from
like one government you know one part to another government you know
area controlled by another government you would also have to do it.
רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is
going to draw the boundaries of the land of Israel for us
okay because until now we've been talking about close or far away
what are the exact boundaries of the land of Israel.
I'm sorry the הגמוניא hegmonia but if it's like let's say all
under control of the Roman Empire and you're going to different you
know.
Yeah so that's not clear right the חידוש chiddush is even if
they're very close but the other the flip side of so are
you saying though it could be as long as it's the same
הגמוניא hegmonia even if it's very far? Right okay all good questions.
רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer you gotta leave the גמרא Gemara
something to do with this משנה. Mishnah. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda
omer now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda draws for us the boundaries of
Israel. מרקם למזרח ורקם כמזרח me-Rekem lemizrach ve-Rekem kemizrach
from רקם Rekem to the east and רקם Rekem is is considered
to be out of Israel so that's the farthest point on the
east. מאשקלון לדרום ואשקלון כדרום me-Ashkelon ledarom ve-Ashkelon kedarom אשקלון Ashkelon to
the south and אשקלון Ashkelon counts as the south so אשקלון Ashkelon
counts as outside of Israel that's very strange right אשקלון Ashkelon is
listed as one of the cities of Israel talk about that in
a minute. מעכו לצפון ועכו כצפון me-Akko letzafon ve-Akko ketzafon from עכו
Akko to the north and עכו Akko Acre is considered to be
outside of Israel part of the north also strange. רבי מאיר אומר
Rabbi Meir omer עכו כארץ ישראל לגיטין Akko k'Eretz Yisrael legittin no
for laws of גיטין Gittin עכו Akko has a status as part
of Israel which is interesting for different laws maybe differently you draw
the borders of Israel differently and I'm gonna come back to that
point in a minute. המביא גט Get, בארץ ישראל *Ha-meivi get b'Eretz
Yisrael*, אינו צריך לומר *eino tzarich lomar* בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם Befanai
Nechtav Befanai Nechtam, *befanai nechtav uvfanai nechtam*. Now finally, if you bring
it in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. *Eretz Yisrael*, you do not have
to say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם Befanai Nechtav Befanai Nechtam? *befanai nechtav
uvfanai nechtam*. Okay, that would be the one thing we didn't talk
about. We talked about from ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* to חוץ לארץ
*chutz la-aretz*, חוץ לארץ *chutz la-aretz* to ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, oh
sorry, excuse me, חוץ לארץ *chutz la-aretz* to ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*,
ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* to חוץ לארץ *chutz la-aretz*, חוץ לארץ *chutz
la-aretz* to חוץ לארץ *chutz la-aretz*, but finally the end of the
משנה Mishnah *mishnah* says in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, where presumably you
know we can check up on things or whatever,
for some reason we don't have to worry about how it was
written, we don't have to why we don't have to be concerned
that the גט Get *get* is a forgery we'll talk about in
the גמרא Gemara. *gemara*, but anyway we're more in control of everything
in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. You don't have to say בפני נכתב
ובפני נחתם bifnei nechtav uvifnei nechtam. *befanai nechtav uvfanai nechtam*. ואם יש
עליו עוררים *V'im yesh alav orerim*, but if there are challenges that
are raised after it's delivered in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* and the
husband comes and says I never wrote that גט Get. *get*, then
יתקיים בחותמיו *yitkayem be-chotmav*. Then the way to deal with those challenges
if and when they arise is you have to get the signatures
validated. So you don't have to validate the signatures at the outset,
but you get the signatures validated and if the signatures were genuinely
signed by the people who signed it, we don't trust the husband
to say that the גט Get *get* was a forgery and that
he never did it. We would say the witnesses would never have
signed it if you had not actually authorized this גט Get *get*.
Now before we get to saying a few more interesting points that
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* makes about this משנה Mishnah, *mishnah*, I do have
to make the following scholarly point as I often use this משנה
Mishnah. *mishnah* in גיטין Gittin *gittin* to make a point about an
interesting phenomenon about משניות *mishnayot*. The גמרא Gemara, *gemara* sometimes refers to,
sometimes even the משנה Mishna, *mishnah* itself refers to משנה Mishna. ראשונה
*Mishnah Rishona* and משנה אחרונה *Mishnah Acharona*, but that usually is clear,
like there's an early teaching and then it got overwritten
later. What is less sort of stated explicitly, but once you realize
it you see it so often, is how sometimes the later תנאים
*Tannaim* received an early simple משנה *mishnah* with basic terms and then
they debated what those terms meant. Okay? So when we normally say
the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* said X and רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda*
says Y and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rebbi Meir* says Z, that's
usually not what happened. Really, the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* said a
simple statement and רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* and רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir*
are debating what the terms of that statement were. Okay? So for
example, the opening משנה *mishnah* in פסחים *Pesachim* is כל מקום שאין
מכניסין בו חמץ אין צריך בדיקה *kol makom she-ein machnisin bo chametz
ein tzarich bdikah*. Where you don't put חמץ *chametz*, you don't have
to check. ולמה אמרו שתי שורות במרתף *Ve-lamah amru shtei shurot ba-martef*?
But what about this teaching of the two rows of the wine
cellar? Why, what does that about? So בית Bayit, שמאי *Beit Shammai*
says it means שתי שורות העליונות שהן החיצונות *shtei shurot ha-elyonot she-hen
ha-chitzonot* and בית הלל *Beit Hillel* says it means these two rows.
So here very clearly it's saying אמרו *amru*, they said two rows
of a wine cellar, what what does that mean? So בית הלל
*Beit Hillel* gives one meaning of it and בית שמאי *Beit Shammai*
gives another. Clearly there's an early teaching and then the later תנאים
*Tannaim*, and that's not late, בית הלל *Beit Hillel* בית שמאי *Beit
Shammai* is early, but anyway a later generation debates what that term
means. So take a look at how this משנה *mishnah* would read
if we took out every named position of this משנה *mishnah*. Just
cross out, not literally, cross out in your imagination every named position
in this משנה *mishnah* and see how this משנה *mishnah* would read
as an early simple משנה *mishnah*. It would read המביא גט Get
ממדינת הים *Ha-meivi get mi-medinat ha-yam*, okay, המביא גט Get ממדינת הים
*Ha-meivi get mi-medinat ha-yam*. What's the next non-named
statement?
והמוליך *Ve-hamolich* והמביא ממדינה
למדינה *ve-hamaveivi mi-medinah le-medinah*, right? And then what's the next non-named statement?
המביא גט Get,
בארץ
ישראל *Ha-meivi get b'Eretz Yisrael*.
גט get בארץ
ישראל *Get b'Eretz Yisrael*, אינו צריך *eino tzarich*. Very simple משנה *mishnah*.
Oh wow, right? If you bring a גט get. *get* from מדינת
הים Medinas Hayam *medinat ha-yam*, צריך שיאמר *tzarich she-yomar*, right? Whatever, right,
בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם bifnei nechtav uvifnei nechtam? *befanai nechtav uvfanai nechtam*.
Okay, if you bring it from מדינת הים Medinas Hayam *medinat ha-yam*
or if you bring it to מדינת הים Medinas Hayam. *medinat ha-yam*
or if you bring it ממדינה למדינה *mi-medinah le-medinah* in מדינת הים
Medinas Hayam, *medinat ha-yam*, but if you bring it in ארץ ישראל
*Eretz Yisrael* you don't have to. What an easy משנה *mishnah*. Comes
along the later תנאים *Tannaim* and they say wait a minute, I
want to understand something. What's this מדינת הים *medinat ha-yam*? Does that
literally mean far away like תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says, or maybe it's
like רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says, maybe it means חוץ לארץ *chutz la-aretz*?
Okay? So comes along whoever it is and says רקם וחגר *Rekem
v'Cheger* and comes along רבי אליעזר *Rebbi Eliezer* says no, no, no,
the מדינת הים *medinat ha-yam*, right, whatever, כקפודקיה לודיא *ke-Kappodokia le-Ludya*. Okay?
וחכמים אומרים *Va-chachamim omerim*, now again what I'm saying, and חכמים *Chachamim*
say no, no, no, it really means מדינת הים *medinat ha-yam*. Okay?
So those
first three positions are just arguing what those words מדינת הים *medinat
ha-yam* mean, right? Okay? And then you get to the end, right,
and now it's a little funny why we left רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* הגמוניא להגמוניא *hegemonya le-hegemonya*, but that's explaining
ממדינה למדינה *mi-medinah le-medinah*, right? רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel* says הגמוניא להגמוניא *hegemonya le-hegemonya*. I'm going to tell you מדינה
Medina מדינה Medina *medinah medinah* does not really mean like you know
big different countries, basically it means even East and West Berlin. Okay?
That's הגמוניא להגמוניא *hegemonya le-hegemonya*. Okay? And then the other issue is
just one minute, before we get on to like המביא גט get
בארץ ישראל *Ha-meivi get b’Eretz Yisrael*, we've got to define what are
the borders of ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, right? Because בתוך ארץ ישראל
*b'toch Eretz Yisrael* or not ארצה *artza*? So the borders of ארץ
ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. Oh, okay. So רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* says these
are the borders, רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir* says those are the borders.
What? Yeah, it could have come after, but this way you end
with the anonymous voice of the משנה *mishnah*. Okay. So they're all
giving clarifying this simple משנה. And once you see that structure, you
see it all the time, and it helps you sort of appreciate,
you know, what's going on. It doesn't become like a complicated lots
of voices.
Yes, and what you're suggesting to me is that
the layered strata of the משנה are already modeling what the אמוראים
Amoraim do explicitly in the גמרא.
Gemara Well, that's an excellent point you're saying. That process continues in
the גמרא, Gemara where we then continue to also debate, etc. But
the גמרא Gemara isn't always debating the terms. Right, right. This is
a little different. This is like there were simple terms, but any
legal law says, well what is the scope of this term? What's
the scope of that term? Right. Exactly. Exactly.
And also, is it not possible for פשט peshat of מדינה here
as many places elsewhere, city and not...
Oh, that's interesting. That's not how the גמרא Gemara, interprets it. I
mean, I don't know if I'd say constantly, but I do get
a sense that it's a larger a larger space. כרך Krakh is
a city. I don't think מדינה is a city. Anyway, we could
talk about it, but that's not how the גמרא Gemara, understands it.
Now, let me make one or two other quick points before we
finally turn the דף, daf, okay? First of all, the word גט,
Get תוספות Tosafot points out is a generic word for a שטר,
Shtar, but but without modification, it's oft it refers to a גיטי
נשים. Gittei Nashim. Why exactly is not clear. תוספות Tosafot also points
out a מנהג Minhag to have twelve lines of a גט Get
in a גט. Get And he says maybe it's because the גימטריה
Gematria of the word גט Get is גט Get. is twelve. But
right, even till today, they write גיטין Gittin, with twelve lines.
Do they fill them up or do they...
No, no, they write the text so that it fills up twelve
lines. Anyway, he gives another interesting interpretation that if it's a book
that divides, so there are twelve, there are between each of the
ספרים Sfarim in the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, we give a gap
of four lines. Between בראשית Bereishit and שמות, Shemot, etc. So between
the first four ספרים, Sfarim, there are three of those gaps, there
are twelve lines
that divide, okay? He says, how about במדבר Bamidbar and דברים? Devarim?
Well, דברים Devarim is just a repetition of whatever, so... okay, move
on. So anyway, okay, the other important part about תוספות Tosafot is
that, I mean there's a lot to say here, but the big
תוספות אשקלון כדרום Tosafot Ashkelon ki-Darom is the question that is really
implicit at the end of the משנה, which is, you're giving these
borders, and רבי מאיר says, wait, for גט Get, purposes, עכו Akko
is like ארץ ישראל. What do you mean for X purposes, for
Y purposes? So the question becomes, and this is going to be
really explored in the גמרא, Gemara. like, what definition, how do we
draw the borders? Like, is it the borders that when they won
the land that they were given in the time of יהושע? Yehoshua?
Is it the borders of the בית שני? Bayit Sheni? Those are
those are borders that determine for like טומאה Tumah and מעשרות, Ma'asrot,
the borders of the בית שני. Bayit Sheni. The borders of בית,
that's more of a question of the קדושה Kedusha of the land.
The borders of יהושע Yehoshua are more the actual boundaries of of
the land. Or do we say, if the concern here has to
do with the ability to know that things were done properly and
so on, it's more based on the on the cultural realities of
what is sort of, you know, the same cultural, governmental, you know,
sort of, you know, well, what's the word? That's, I guess cultural.
Anyway, you know, what what...
You mean political?
Yeah, but not exactly political, but something like that. Meaning, like, what's
the boundaries in which is where בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, you know,
where the Jewish people are living in the Land of Israel, that
defines like the cultural boundaries of the Land of Israel? 'Cause we'll
see in the גמרא, Gemara if the question is that you might
not be able to find witnesses 'cause it's far away or they
might not have done it properly, so you're in ask more practical
questions, which is: well, is this place far a different enough? You
know, if it's the עיקר היישוב, Ikkar Ha-Yishuv, then it's okay, but
if it's a place that's more somewhere, you know, somewhere out in
the boondocks or whatever, they might not know what they're doing and
we might not be able to get witnesses from there. So it
might not be standard borders of the Land of Israel. So for
example, when תוספות Tosafot. points out that these places like אשקלון Ashkelon
and עכו Akko are clearly part of Israel, תוספות Tosafot says, yes,
but maybe they're too far at the margins, you know, at the
periphery, that for the purposes of why we're saying בפני נכתב ובפני
נחתם, bifnei nechtav uvifnei nechtam, that doesn't count as Israel. So this
is going to be an ongoing question in the in the in
this first, you know, the first few דפים, Dappim, which is, do
we use standard definitions of the borders of Israel, or do we
draw the map based on the concerns that are unique to this
הלכה Halakha of בפני נכתב bifnei nechtav. ובפני נחתם? Nichtam Yeah, and
אשקלון Ashkelon
is in
ארץ פלשתים Eretz Pelishtim also.
Right, so whether that matters or whatever. Right,
long תוספות. Tosafot Now, one more line, I know we have to
turn the דף, daf, but I have to say one more thing.
Okay, אם יש עליו עורר מתקיים בחותמיו. Im yesh alav orer mitkayem
be-chotmav. If the גט Get, is challenged, so תוספות Tosafos says, look
at the first line of תוספות אם יש עליו עורר. Tosafot Im
yesh alav orer. תוספות Tosafos says like this, he says,
אם יש עליו עורר מתקיים בחותמיו, Im yesh alav orer mitkayem be-chotmav,
אבל כל זמן דלא אתא בעל מערער, aval kol zman dlo ata
ba'al me-arer, the husband doesn't come and challenge the גט, get. this
is when it's being brought in Israel, נישאת על פי גט. niset
al pi Get. She can get married, okay, ולא תנינן מזויף. ve-lo
taninan mezuyaf. We don't say, why don't we say the husband's not
here, we have to defend the husband's interest, so we the בית
דין... Beit Din... If something is happening in the absence of the
other party, we have to defend the interests of the other party,
so we will challenge the גט and say maybe it's forged? No,
we don't do that, we don't stand in for the husband's interests
and make that challenge. Why not? דמשום עיגונא אקילו בה רבנן, De'mishum
iguna akilu bah rabanan, because for concerns of עגונה, aguna, the Rabbis
were lenient, they did not want this woman to have to not
be able to get married until she could find witnesses, so for
that way we do not, we do not like represent the husband's
interests and challenge the גט. Now I did not bring that in
so I could point out the words דמשום עיגונא אקילו בה רבנן
de'mishum iguna akilu bah rabanan in the first דף daf of גיטין,
Gittin. although it is a good thing to point out. But the
reason I brought that in was because
רמב״ן Ramban responds to תוספות Tosafos and says the reason we don't
say that maybe it was a forgery and to defend the husband's
interests is because, he says, the woman is not the husband's property,
and therefore it's not like it's his interest like we're taking something
from him that you now have to represent. Like if I was
trying
to seize your property and you weren't around, we would have to
defend you in your absence, okay? But he says this is a
woman who's trying to define her legal status, okay? So he says
אין האשה נכסי הבעל ein ha'ishah nichsei haba'al or something like that,
that we would have to treat it like a דיני ממונות dinei
mamonos case where you have to defend the other party's interest. So
I think that's really interesting right at the outset, you know, because
the husband is really so much in control to think conceptually about
how that act is understood and about to what degree, you know,
the woman is seen as the husband's property in this whole process.
Yes, Charlie.
רמב״ן Ramban is defining outside the realm of דיני ממונות. dinei mamonos.
Is it possible to conceptualize this as still within the realm of
דיני ממונות dinei mamonos but we've made an exception here?
That's what תוספות Tosafos says, דמשום עיגונא אקילו בה
רבנן.
de'mishum iguna akilu
bah rabanan.
Yeah, no, that's what תוספות Tosafos says. What I'm saying, nobody says
that you defend, everybody says you don't say maybe it's a forge,
we don't defend the husband, that's the whole point of the משנה.
תוספות Tosafos says it's because of עגונה. aguna. רמב״ן Ramban says it's
not because of עגונה, aguna, it's because fundamentally it is not seen
as taking something from the husband.
סוף סוף, sof sof, he sees it as taking something from the
husband. The husband is the party as a party that is being
injured in this process, you know, and therefore we have to go
ahead and represent his side.
Yes, but it depends how you see what the husband's interests are,
because in a marriage he doesn't want to be in, it's in
his interest to divorce her, so by not challenging you are defending
his interest.
Well, that's an interesting, that's what I think essentially what the רמב״ן
Ramban is saying. If you see this as property then it's one
thing, property is being taken away from a person. If you see
it as a relationship, right, you don't know what the interests are
in terms of the relationship and you see it in different ways.
I think that's a nice way of saying essentially what the way
of seeing what the רמב״ן Ramban is saying. Let's finally now start
the גמרא. Gemara Okay. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What is the reason
you have to say this? So רבה אמר, Rabbah amar, you have
to say בפני נכתב bifnei nechtav, ובפני נחתם. Nichtam. רבה אמר Rabbah
amar לפי שאין בקיאין לשמה, lefi she'ein beki'in lishmah, because they don't
know out in מדינת הים that you have to write the גט
for the sake of the woman, and therefore we're afraid it was
not written according to הלכה. halacha. רבה Rabbah is focusing on the
words בפני נכתב. bifnei nechtav If you have to testify to how
it's written, so you have to know, that means that there's a
question whether it was written correctly. Now תוספות Tosafos says why specifically
לשמה? lishmah? Like, so he says, well, maybe that was the most
prevalent problem, but maybe, you know, but other problems were less prevalent,
but it really is a general concern that they don't know the
laws of גיטין. Gittin. Okay, that I think is the thing that
makes the most sense. But then תוספות Tosafos... has other reasons to
say no, no, it actually seems they did know the other laws
of גיטין. Gittin So תוספות Tosafos says, well, maybe it means that
for some reason they didn't buy into the לשמה lishmah requirement, so
they don't know the laws of לשמה lishmah really means they don't
buy into it, they're not always so good about the requirement of
לשמה. lishmah.
Meaning like standard גיטין Gittin with standard names in them?
Something like that, right, right, right, something like that. Okay, but anyway,
one way or another way, it means there's a question whether it
was written כפי ההלכה kefi hahalacha and that's רבה Rabbah focused on
בפני נכתב, Bifnay Nichtav, so you have to testify to that fact.
Okay, I always when I learned this, I learned this I think
it was in eleventh grade, and the question that always bothered me
was, wait a minute, if they don't know the הלכות, halachos, then
how do they know that they have to get the שליח shaliach
to say בפני נכתב Nichtav ובפני נחתם? But the answer is like
obvious. Once in Israel they start rejecting גיטין when the guy comes
without saying it, they very quickly learn that we're only going to
get them delivered in Israel if we actually, if the שליח shaliach
testifies to this. Okay, and then hopefully then they also understand what
it is he testifies to and they actually maybe are more careful
about לשמה, lishmah, but anyway, that's why, or maybe the point is
no, maybe if they don't know, maybe if they're not careful about
הלכה, halacha, he won't say בפני נכתב Nichtav because they won't know
הלכה halacha in general and that'll exactly solve the problem. When he's
saying בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, it shows us that they know what
they're doing, which raises another issue which is, how does saying it
was written in front of me mean that it was done with
לשמה? lishmah? All you're saying is it was written in front of
you. So רש״י Rashi... says two possibilities. One is either then we
inquire and we say, oh okay, tell us a little bit more,
what how exactly was it done,
and
so on and
so forth. no, it's an implicit saying it was written in front
of me is an implicit claim that it was done כפי ההלכה.
K'fi HaHalacha. And we don't have to actually inquire anymore. And maybe
it is a little tied into what I said: if they know
the requirement that they're going to have to claim בפני נכתב, they
know that there's something that they're testifying to. Okay, so that's... now,
hold on, we're going to just read a little more. So that
is one aspect of לשמה. Lishma. רבה אמר, Raba Amar, לפי שאין
עדים מצויים לקיימו. Lefi She'ain Eidim Metzuyim Lekaymo. No,
רבא Rava focuses on בפני נחתם. Bifnay Nichtam. And רבא Rava says
that the problem is is that if this גט is challenged as
we see at the end that it's a forgery, you're going to
have to find witnesses to either testify that it's their signature or
witnesses that can identify that it's this, yes, I recognize Michael's signature
and this is Michael's signature. That's considered נתקיים בחותמיו. Nitkayem Bechotmav. Either
the witnesses themselves or other witnesses.
Or have a receipt, give me like a backdated document, right?
Yeah, but that wouldn't in this case. Anyway, yes, so anyway רבא
Rava says, so we see at the end that when that a
גט that's delivered without claim to its legitimacy is open to challenge.
And if it does get challenged, you have to find witnesses. So
he says here's the problem: that we can do in Israel, because
if it's all takes place internally, we'll just send for the witnesses.
Okay, we'll send for people who recognize the signatures. But if it's
coming from some far away place and the גט is challenged, who
that, when are we ever going to be able to find witnesses
to testify to the signatures? So we better get it validated right
now. Okay, and we're going to get the שליח Shaliach to validate
it and say it was legitimately signed. And normally we need two
people to validate it, here it's one, the גמרא Gemara. will get
to that. Right, before notaries. Okay, but that's right, before notaries. Okay,
that's the purpose, the purpose is בפני נחתם, Bifnay Nichtam, that we
don't want a challenge that it was a forgery and he has
to testify to that. So that's basically the debate, the נכתב or
the נחתם part. By the way, I have to tell you, when
I was learning this, I kept on getting רבה Raba and רבא
Rava is not an easy debate. Wait wait, which one did רבה
Raba say, which one
did רבא Rava say? So here's the mnemonic I figured out in
eleventh grade, which is רבה Raba ends with ה, Heh, רבה Raba
is לשמה, Lishma, okay, which ends with a ה. Heh. That's how
I figured it out. Okay, רבא Rava is the other one. Okay,
now, we have seven minutes, we'll have to hold it off. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: Now, מאי בינייהו? Mai Binaihu?
Such a great גמרא. Gemara Before we even analyze the משנה, let's
talk about conceptually, a priori, if you have two different reasons, what
would be some נפקא מינא Nafka Minos whether it's about לשמה Lishma
or whether it's being able to validate the signatures? And the גמרא
Gemara spells out some very obvious נפקא מינא. Nafka Minos. איכא בינייהו,
Ika Binaihu, here are some differences: דאתו בי תרי, De'asu Bei Trei,
two people brought it. We don't have to worry about validating, we
have two witnesses here. Okay, but we still have to worry if
it's coming from מדינת הים that they didn't know what they were
doing, that they didn't know the הלכה, Halacha, לשמה. Lishma. Now, רש״י...
Rashi. now the question is what do you mean we don't have
to worry about validating? I mean, what are the two people going
to do? תוספות... Tosafos, what are we going to do, lock them
in jail for ten years so that they're available to us if
we need to validate? They're going to go back to מדינת הים.
So תוספות Tosafot says what: no, but their very delivery of it
is like testifying to the fact that the husband sent them. Like,
you know, the fact that it's two
witnesses, you know, even without saying anything, they're essentially testifying to their
own role of being witnesses and being sent by the husband, and
therefore we don't have to be concerned the גט will be challenged.
It's a little complicated. Yeah,
they just show up and just deliver it, right? Okay, I mean
they say that they were sent by the husband, but they don't
have to testify that it was signed and sealed in front of
them. And the fact that they're testifying that they were sent by
the husband, says תוספות, Tosafot means we don't have to concern ourselves
that the husband will challenge the גט. Okay. Anyway, two people brought
it, but okay, maybe it was legitimately sent by the husband, but
it might not be
לשמה. Lishma. אינמי ממדינה למדינה בארץ ישראל. Inami M'medina L'medina B'eretz Yisrael.
Okay, some of these cases seem to already be answered in the
משנה. From one region to another in Israel, like יהודה וגליל. Yehuda
V'Galil. So it could be everybody in Israel knows לשמה, Lishma, but
maybe there's not a lot of travel between two regions and maybe
it would still be hard to get witnesses from one region to
another. So a place where they know לשמה, Lishma, but there's still
a travel problem and a witnesses problem. Okay, אינמי, Inami, okay, אינמי
Inami or a third נפקא מינא, Nafka Mina, באותה מדינה במדינת הים,
Be'osah Medina B'medinas Hayam, right? It's all within one country in מדינת
הים, where they don't know לשמה Lishma well enough, but it's within
one country so they'll be able to find witnesses. Okay, a lot
of nice hypothetical נפקא מינא. Nafka Minos. Not everything that's a hypothetical
נפקא מינא Nafka Mina will play out that way, but a very
beautiful conceptual explanation of is it נכתב or is it נחתם. Here's
the conceptual differences, here are the נפקא מינא. Nafka Minos. Let's read
one line in the גמרא Gemara to get us to why is
it that one witness suffices to address these concerns. Okay, ולרבה דאמר
לפי שאין בקיאין לשמה, Ul'Raba De'amar Lefi She'ain Beki'in Lishma, רבה Raba
who says that the problem is that they don't know the laws
of לשמה Lishma and that's what you're testifying to, מיבעי תרי? Miba'ei
Trei? Why don't we need two? If you want to... if there's
a real doubt whether it's a legitimate גט, a כשר Kosher גט,
right? Not forged, that's not the issue, but the issue is כשר.
Kosher. in terms of the הלכות, halachas, okay, you should need two
witnesses to testify. Why? מידי דהוה אכל עדיות שבתורה, midi dehavah akol
eduyos shebaTorah, like all testimonies require two. Okay, and this is testifying
to the legitimacy of the גט. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
עד אחד נאמן באיסורין. ed echad ne'eman b'issurin. When it comes to
something's כשרות kashrus status, we trust one witness. And how do you
know this? Beautiful רש״י. Rashi, Look at רש״י, Rashi's עד אחד נאמן
באיסורין, ed echad ne'eman b'issurin, five lines down in the narrow lines,
שהרי הימנה תורה כל אחד ואחד מישראל על הפרשת תרומה ועל השחיטה
ועל ניקור
הגיד והחלב. sheharei hemina Torah kol echad v'echad miYisrael al hafrashat terumah
v'al hashchitah v'al nikur hagid v'hachelev. Okay, you go to the butcher
and you trust him that he שחט shachted it. I mean, they
didn't have a whole OU השגחה hashgacha industry. People were able to
testify for themselves or as תוספות Tosafot says, היכא אנו סומכין על
נשותינו? heicha anu somchin al neshotenu? How do we rely on our
wives? Okay, we go home and they say they're giving us כשר
kosher food or that they were or they salted the meat because
you would go to the butcher, you'd buy unsalted meat. How do
we trust people about that? How do we trust women that they
go to the מקוה? mikvah? Okay, so עד אחד נאמן באיסורין, ed
echad ne'eman b'issurin, when it comes to something's כשרות kashrus status, you
rely on a single witness. Do you want to say something Jenna?
Isn't there a thing with מקוה mikvah bringing home a receipt?
Yeah, that's what I don't know. That's not a הלכה. halacha. Okay,
really? I got to tell you, all my life for never brought
me home a receipt. Okay, anyway, so
the גמרא says one minute, אימור דאמרינן עד אחד נאמן באיסורין, eimur
d'amrinan ed echad ne'eman b'issurin, when do we say one witness suffices
to establish something's כשרות kashrus status? כגון חתיכה ספק של חלב ספק
של שומן. kegon chatichah safek shel chelev safek shel shuman. If you
have a piece of meat in front of you and you don't
know, is it non-כשר kosher fat or כשר kosher fat? Okay, and
the witness can tell you, I'll tell you what it is. ולא
איתחזק איסורא, v'lo it-chazak issura, we never started knowing that it was
אסור. assur. Okay, so therefore we just don't know. So a witness
tells
us. אבל הכא דאיתחזק איסורא דאשת איש, aval hacha d'it-chazak issura d'eshet
ish, we knew that the woman originally was married. So how can
you trust one witness to change the status? הוי דבר שבערוה havei
davar sheb'ervah and not only that, not only is it against א
חזקה, a chazakah, but also this is a matter of עריות arayos
ואין דבר שבערוה פחות משנים v'ein davar sheb'ervah pachot mishnayim and that
requires two witnesses.
So so how can it be? A, דאיתחזק איסורא, d'it-chazak issura, we
know she was forbidden and you shouldn't be able to trust one
witness. And number two, it's עריות arayos and you should always need
two in a matter of עריות. arayos. So how do we trust
one? So I'm going to leave you with that cliffhanger. We'll see
the answer tomorrow. Look at that, I finished before 8:30. But I
do want to say one thing which is about איתחזק איסורא, it-chazak
issura, which is רש״י examples are איתחזק איסורא. it-chazak issura. If you
have a piece of meat, it used to be אבר מן החי,
eiver min hachai, you don't know that it was שחט shachted correctly.
You don't know that the blood was removed. You don't know that
the חלב chelev was removed. Those are איתחזק איסורא. it-chazak issura. So
תוספות introduces the important concept of
בידו. beyado. I'm already using my hand, בידו. beyado. If you have
the ability to change the status, you're believed against איתחזק איסורא. it-chazak
issura. In theory, you could שחט shacht or hire somebody to שחט,
shacht, hire somebody to remove the fat or hire some or remove
it yourself or salt the meat yourself. But the woman or the
שליח shaliach cannot divorce on their own. Right, they cannot no matter
how much money they spend and how many people they hire, unless
the בעל baal agrees, they're not she's not going to get divorced.
It's not בידו. beyado. And therefore if it's not בידו, beyado, it's
איתחזק איסורא, it-chazak issura, you don't believe עד אחד. ed echad. תוספות
does say however, there are some opinions that you even do believe
עד אחד ed echad against איתחזק איסורא. it-chazak issura. And that's why
the גמרא adds the point of it's an ערווה. ervah. So there
are two reasons here why you should need two witnesses. It's a
חזקת איסור chazakas issur and it's not בידו beyado and a חזקת
איסור chazakas issur needs two witnesses. And even for those that think
a חזקת איסור chazakas issur doesn't need two witnesses, one witness suffices,
it's an ערווה ervah case. So you should need two witnesses and
we will find out tomorrow what the answer to that is.